For the last year,
خلال السنة الماضية،
everyone's been watching the same show,
كان الجميع يشاهدون نفس المشاهد.
and I'm not talking about "Game of Thrones,"
وأنا هنا لا أتحدث عن مسلسل"صراع العروش"
but a horrifying, real-life drama
وإنما عن دراما مرعبة وحقيقة
that's proved too fascinating to turn off.
وقد أثبتت أنها رائعة جداً بحيث لا يمكن إيقافها.
It's a show produced by murderers
إنه عرضٌ أنتجه السفاحون
and shared around the world via the Internet.
وقد تم نشره حول العالم عبر الانترنت
Their names have become familiar:
وقد أضحت أسماؤهم مشهورةً ومألوفة:
James Foley, Steven Sotloff, David Haines, Alan Henning, Peter Kassig,
جيمس فولي، وستيفن سوتلوف، وديفيد هانيس، وآلان هينينغ، وبيتير كاسيغ
Haruna Yukawa, Kenji Goto Jogo.
وهارونا يوكاوا وكينجي غوتو جوغو.
Their beheadings by the Islamic State
تعتبر عمليات نحرهم بواسطة داعش
were barbaric,
همجية،
but if we think they were archaic,
ولكن إذا تصورنا أنها قديمة
from a remote, obscure age,
وتعود لعصور بعيدة وغير معروفة
then we're wrong.
فإننا سنكون على خطأ.
They were uniquely modern,
إن عمليات الإعدام كانت فريدةً ومعاصرةً
because the murderers acted knowing well
لأن السفاحين قاموا بذلك باحترافية
that millions of people would tune in to watch.
مما حث ملايين الناس لمشاهدة أفعالهم.
The headlines called them savages and barbarians,
إن العناوين الرئيسية للأخبار وصفتهم بالهمجيين البرابرة،
because the image of one man overpowering another,
لأنها صورة لرجل يطغى على الآخر.
killing him with a knife to the throat,
و يقتله بواسطة سكين يشق حلقه
conforms to our idea of ancient, primitive practices,
بشكل يتوافق مع الممارسات البدائية القديمة،
the polar opposite of our urban, civilized ways.
ويتناقض مع تمدننا وتحضرنا.
We don't do things like that.
لا نقوم بأمور من هذا القبيل.
But that's the irony.
وهنا تكمن المفارقة.
We think a beheading has nothing to do with us,
لأننا نعتقد أن قطع الرؤوس لا علاقة له بنا،
even as we click on the screen to watch.
حتى عندما نقوم بمشاهدتها على الشاشة.
But it is to do with us.
ولكنها مرتبطة ومتعلقة بنا.
The Islamic State beheadings
إن عمليات قطع الرؤوس من طرف "الدولة الإسلامية"
are not ancient or remote.
ليست بقديمة ولا ببعيدة.
They're a global, 21st century event,
إنها أحداث عالمية وتحدث في القرن الحادي والعشرين
a 21st century event that takes place in our living rooms, at our desks,
إنه حدثٌ في القرن الواحد والعشرين يحدث في غرف معيشتنا وعلى مقاعدنا.
on our computer screens.
وعلى شاشات حواسيبنا.
They're entirely dependent on the power of technology to connect us.
إنهم يعتمدون بشكلٍ كلي على قوة التكنولوجيا للتواصل معنا
And whether we like it or not,
سواء أحببنا ذلك أم كرهناه.
everyone who watches is a part of the show.
يعتبر كل شخص يقوم بمشاهدة ولو جزءٍ من ذلك العرض متواطئا في ذلك.
And lots of people watch.
والكثير من الناس تشاهد ذلك.
We don't know exactly how many.
لا نعلم عددهم على وجه التحديد.
Obviously, it's difficult to calculate.
فمن الواضح أنه يصعب إحصاؤهم.
But a poll taken in the UK, for example, in August 2014,
ولكن أًجري استطلاع للرأي في المملكة المتحدة، في شهر أغسطس في 2014
estimated that 1.2 million people
قدّر أن مليون ومئتي ألف شخص
had watched the beheading of James Foley
شاهدوا عملية قطع رأس جيمس فولي
in the few days after it was released.
بعد عدة أيام من نشر الفيديو.
And that's just the first few days,
وهذا فقط بعد مضي بضعة أيام،
and just Britain.
وفي بريطانيا فقط.
A similar poll taken in the United States
كما أُجري استطلاع مشابه في الولايات المتحدة
in November 2014
في نوفمبر 2014
found that nine percent of those surveyed
أبرز أن 9% من الذين شملهم الاستطلاع
had watched beheading videos,
شاهدوا عمليات قطع الرؤوس،
and a further 23 percent
وأن حوالي 23 % منهم
had watched the videos but had stopped just before the death was shown.
شاهدوا الفيديوهات ولكن توقفوا قبل لحظة الذبح تماماً.
Nine percent may be a small minority of all the people who could watch,
و 9% تبدو نسبة ضئيلة من كل الذين يمكنهم المشاهدة
but it's still a very large crowd.
ولكنه يعتبر بالفعل حشدا كبيرا.
And of course that crowd is growing all the time,
وبالطبع فإن العدد في تزايد مستمر مع الوقت،
because every week, every month,
لأنه في كل أسبوع، وكل شهر
more people will keep downloading and keep watching.
سيواصل المزيد والمزيد من الناس تنزيل ومشاهدة المقاطع.
If we go back 11 years,
وإذا ما عدنا 11 سنة للوراء
before sites like YouTube and Facebook were born,
قبل إنشاء مواقع كاليوتيوب والفايسبوك
it was a similar story.
فإن القصة كانت مشابهة.
When innocent civilians like Daniel Pearl,
فعندما تُفصل رؤوس المدنيين الأبرياء مثل دانيال بيرل
Nick Berg, Paul Johnson, were beheaded,
و نيك بيرغ، وبول جونسون،
those videos were shown during the Iraq War.
نعلم أنه هذه الفيديوهات ظهرت خلال الحرب العراقية
Nick Berg's beheading
وعملية ذبح نيك بيرغ
quickly became one of the most searched for items on the Internet.
سرعان ما أصبحت أحد اكثر المواضيع بحثا عنها في الإنترنت.
Within a day, it was the top search term
فخلال يوم واحد، كانت أكثر ما تم البحث عنه
across search engines like Google, Lycos, Yahoo.
عبر محركات غوغل وليكوس وياهو.
In the week after Nick Berg's beheading,
وبعد أسبوع على قطع رأس نيك بيرغ،
these were the top 10 search terms in the United States.
أضحت من أهم 10 عبارات بحث في الولايات المتحدة.
The Berg beheading video remained the most popular search term for a week,
و ظلت عبارة "عملية فصل رأس بيرغ" الأكثر شعبية طيلة أسبوع،
and it was the second most popular search term for the whole month of May,
وأضحت في المرتبة الثانية كامل شهر مايو
runner-up only to "American Idol."
فلم يتجاوزها سوى "أميريكان أيدول".
The al-Qaeda-linked website that first showed Nick Berg's beheading
موقع تنظيم القاعدة كان أول من بث عملية قطع رأس نيك بيرغ.
had to close down within a couple of days due to overwhelming traffic to the site.
ثم أُغلق بعد يومين بسبب الضغط الزائد على الموقع.
One Dutch website owner said that his daily viewing figures
وأحد المواقع الألمانية صرّح أن عدد الزيارات اليومية له
rose from 300,000 to 750,000
ارتفع من 300 ألف إلى 750 ألف
every time a beheading in Iraq was shown.
كلما قام بعرض عملية قطع للرؤوس في العراق.
He told reporters 18 months later
وقد أخبر المراسلين بعد 18 شهرا
that it had been downloaded many millions of times,
أنه تم تنزيل الفيديوهات ملايين المرات
and that's just one website.
وهذا مجرد موقع واحد.
A similar pattern was seen again and again
ونفس النمط تكرر ومراراً
when videos of beheadings were released during the Iraq War.
كلما ظهرت فيديوهات لقطع الرؤوس خلال حرب العراق.
Social media sites have made these images more accessible than ever before,
إن مواقع التواصل الاجتماعي سهلت عملية الحصول على هذه المشاهد أكثر من أي وقت مضى،
but if we take another step back in history,
ولكن إذا ما رجعنا خطوة أخرى للوراء في التاريخ
we'll see that it was the camera that first created a new kind of crowd
فإننا سنرى أن الكاميرا هي التي أنشأت أول نوع من الحشود
in our history of beheadings as public spectacle.
في تاريخ مشاهد قطع الرؤوس كنوع من العروض العلنية.
As soon as the camera appeared on the scene,
وحالما ظهرت الكاميرا في موقع الحدث
a full lifetime ago on June 17, 1939,
منذ جيل كامل، في 17 يونيو عام 1939.
it had an immediate and unequivocal effect.
كان لها تأثير مباشر وغير معقول.
That day, the first film of a public beheading was created in France.
في ذلك اليوم تم إنشاء أول فيلم عن قطع الرؤوس في فرنسا
It was the execution, the guillotining, of a German serial killer, Eugen Weidmann,
وقد كان إعدام القاتل المتسلسل و السفاح الألماني، إيغون ويدمان،
outside the prison Saint-Pierre in Versailles.
خارج سجن ساينت بيتر في فيرساي.
Weidmann was due to be executed at the crack of dawn,
كان من المقرر إعدام ويدمان عند بزوغ الفجر،
as was customary at the time,
كما كان متبعا آنذاك،
but his executioner was new to the job,
ولكن الجلاد المكلف بالمهمة كان جدبدا في هذا المنصب،
and he'd underestimated how long it would take him to prepare.
وأخطئ بتقدير المدة التي يحتاجها للاستعداد.
So Weidmann was executed at 4:30 in the morning,
بالتالي تم إعدام ويدمان عند الساعة 4 ونصف صباحا،
by which time on a June morning,
وكان ذلك صبيحة يوم من أيام يونيو،
there was enough light to take photographs,
كان هناك ما يكفي من الضوء لالتقاط صور فوتوغرافية،
and a spectator in the crowd filmed the event,
وقام متفرج في الحشد بتصوير الحدث،
unbeknownst to the authorities.
بدون علم السلطات.
Several still photographs were taken as well,
تم كذلك التقاط العديد من الصور الثابتة،
and you can still watch the film online today
ولازال بإمكانك إلى حد اليوم مشاهدة الفيلم على الإنترنت
and look at the photographs.
وإلقاء نظرة على الصور.
The crowd on the day of Weidmann's execution
أطلقت الصحافة على الحشد الذي حضر عملية إعدام ويدمان
was called "unruly" and "disgusting" by the press,
أوصافا منها "الجامح" و"مثير للاشمئزاز"،
but that was nothing compared to the untold thousands of people
ولكن هذا يعتبر لا شيء مقارنةً بعدد الناس الذي يصعب حصر عددهم
who could now study the action
والذين يمكنكهم الآن دراسة هذه التصرفات
over and over again,
مرارا وتكرارا،
freeze-framed in every detail.
مع التوقف والتدقيق في كل التفاصيل.
The camera may have made these scenes more accessible than ever before,
ربما جعلت الكاميرا الحصول على هذه المشاهد أكثر سهولة من أي وقت مضى،
but it's not just about the camera.
ولكن لا يتعلق الأمر بالكاميرا فقط.
If we take a bigger leap back in history,
ولكن إذا نظرنا إلى الماضي،
we'll see that for as long as there have been
سنرى أنه لطالما وُجد
public judicial executions and beheadings,
الإعدام القضائي في العلن وقطع الرؤوس،
there have been the crowds to see them.
وكانت حشود تتجمع لرؤيتهم.
In London, as late as the early 19th century,
في لندن، في أواخر القرن 19،
there might be four or five thousand people to see a standard hanging.
يقدر عدد الذين رأوا قاعدة الشنق بحوالي أربعة أو خمسة ألاف شخص.
There could be 40,000 or 50,000 to see a famous criminal killed.
وربما يكون هناك 40،000 أو 50،000 شخصا رأوا عملية قتل مجرم مشهورٍ.
And a beheading, which was a rare event in England at the time,
وتعتبر عملية قطع الرؤوس حدثا نادرا في إنجلترا في ذلك الوقت،
attracted even more.
مما تسبب بجذب المزيد.
In May 1820,
في مايو من عام 1820،
five men known as the Cato Street Conspirators
تم تنفيذ حكم بالإعدام على خمسة رجال اشتهروا باسم متآمري كاتو ستريت
were executed in London for plotting
في لندن وذلك بتهمة التآمر
to assassinate members of the British government.
لاغتيالهم أعضاء في الحكومة البريطانية.
They were hung and then decapitated.
كانوا معلقين ثم تم قطع رؤوسهم.
It was a gruesome scene.
كان المشهد بشعا.
Each man's head was hacked off in turn and held up to the crowd.
تم إسناد رأس كل واحد منهم إلى الوراء بالتناوب وإظهاره للحشد.
And 100,000 people,
و100،000 شخص،
that's 10,000 more than can fit into Wembley Stadium,
يزيدون ب10000عن الطاقة الاستيعابية لملعب ويمبلي،
had turned out to watch.
وقد قدموا لمشاهدة ذلك.
The streets were packed.
واكتظت الشوارع.
People had rented out windows and rooftops.
قام الجميع اجتياح النوافذ وأسطح المباني.
People had climbed onto carts and wagons in the street.
قام الناس بتسلق العربات والمركبات في الشوارع.
People climbed lamp posts.
كما قاموا بتسلق أعمدة الإنارة.
People had been known to have died in the crush on popular execution days.
وقد كان معروفا أن الكثير يلقى حتفه في أيام تنفيذ الإعدام بسبب التدافع.
Evidence suggests that throughout our history
وتشير الأدلة أنه على طول تاريخنا
of public beheadings and public executions,
في تنفيذ عمليات قطع الرؤوس العامة والإعدامات العلنية،
the vast majority of the people who come to see
تكون الأغلبية الساحقة من الشعب الذين يأتون لرؤيتها
are either enthusiastic or, at best, unmoved.
إما متحمسين وإما لا مبالين، في أحسن الأحوال.
Disgust has been comparatively rare,
وقد كان الشعور بالاشمئزاز نادرا نسبيا،
and even when people are disgusted and are horrified,
وحتى عندما يكون الناس يشعرون بالاشمئزاز والرعب،
it doesn't always stop them from coming out all the same to watch.
لا يمنعهم ذلك من الحضور المتكرر ومشاهدة مثل هذه الأمور.
Perhaps the most striking example
ولعل أبرز مثال
of the human ability to watch a beheading and remain unmoved
على قدرة الإنسان على مشاهدة عملية قطع الرؤوس ويبقى غير متأثر بذلك
and even be disappointed
أو حتى يشعر بخيبة الأمل
was the introduction in France in 1792 of the guillotine,
هو عندما تم تقديم المقصلة في فرنسا عام 1792،
that famous decapitation machine.
آلة قطع الرأس الشهيرة.
To us in the 21st century,
بالنسبة لنا في القرن 21،
the guillotine may seem like a monstrous contraption,
قد تبدو المقصلة كشيء قبيح وفظيعٍ،
but to the first crowds who saw it, it was actually a disappointment.
ولكن بالنسبة لأول الذين رأوها، فقد كانت في الواقع مخيبةً للآمال.
They were used to seeing long, drawn-out, torturous executions on the scaffold,
فقد كانوا معتادين على رؤية عملية تعذيب طويلة جدا على منصة الإعدام،
where people were mutilated and burned and pulled apart slowly.
حيث يتم جدع الناس وحرقهم وجرهم بعيدا ببطء.
To them, watching the guillotine in action,
بالنسبة لهم، مشاهدة المصقلة عند عملية الإعدام،
it was so quick, there was nothing to see.
كانت عملية سريعة ولم يكن هناك شيء يستحق المشاهدة.
The blade fell, the head fell into a basket, out of sight immediately,
نزلت الشفرة، سقط الرأس في السلة، بعيدا عن الأنظار على الفور،
and they called out,
وعندها احتجوا،
"Give me back my gallows, give me back my wooden gallows."
"أعيدوا إلينا المشنقة، أعيدوا إلينا مشنقتنا الخشبية."
The end of torturous public judicial executions in Europe and America
كانت نهاية عملية الإعدام القانونية والعلنية في كل من أوروبا وأمريكا
was partly to do with being more humane towards the criminal,
كجزء من معاملة المجرمين بطريقة أكثر إنسانيةً،
but it was also partly because the crowd obstinately refused to behave
ولكن يعود هذا أيضا بسبب رفض الحشود التصرف
in the way that they should.
بالطريقة المناسبة.
All too often, execution day
في كثير من الأحيان، كان يوم تنفيذ الإعدام
was more like a carnival than a solemn ceremony.
أشبه بكرنفال من احتفالٍ رسمي.
Today, a public judicial execution in Europe or America is unthinkable,
أما اليوم،أصبح تنفيذ عملية إعدام قضائي علني في أوروبا أو أمريكا غير وارد،
but there are other scenarios that should make us cautious
ولكن توجد سيناريوهات أخرى ينبغي أن تجعلنا نأخذ حذرنا
about thinking that things are different now
بأننا نظن أن الأمور أصبحت مختلفة الآن
and we don't behave like that anymore.
وأننا لا نتصرف مثل ذلك بعد الآن.
Take, for example, the incidents of suicide baiting.
لنأخذ على سبيل المثال عمليات الانتحار التي تعتبر مغرية.
This is when a crowd gathers
فعندما يتجمع حشد من الناس
to watch a person who has climbed to the top of a public building
لمشاهدة شخص صعد إلى سطح مبنى عام
in order to kill themselves,
لوضع حدٍّ لحياته،
and people in the crowd shout and jeer,
والناس يهتفون ويسخرون منه،
"Get on with it! Go on and jump!"
"هيا أكمل ذلك! قم بالقفز!"
This is a well-recognized phenomenon.
هذه ظاهرة معروفة تماما.
One paper in 1981 found that in 10 out of 21 threatened suicide attempts,
أجري بحث في عام 1981 أثبت أن 10 من 21 محاولاتً توعد بالقيام بالانتحار،
there was incidents of suicide baiting and jeering from a crowd.
كانت هناك حوادث انتحار بسبب الإغراء والاستهزاء من الجماهير.
And there have been incidents reported in the press this year.
وكما وردت حوادث في الصحافة هذا العام.
This was a very widely reported incident
وكان وقع نشر هذا الحادث على نطاق واسع جدا
in Telford and Shropshire in March this year.
في كل من تيلفورد وشروبشاير مارس هذا العام.
And when it happens today,
وعندما يحدث هذا اليوم،
people take photographs and they take videos on their phones
يقوم الناس بالتقاط صورٍ ومقاطع فيديو باستعمال هواتفهم
and they post those videos online.
ويقومون بتحميلها على الإنترنت.
When it comes to brutal murderers who post their beheading videos,
عندما يتعلق الأمر بالقتلة المتوحشين الذين ينشرون مقاطع لعمليات ذبح قاموا بها،
the Internet has created a new kind of crowd.
أنشأ الإنترنت نوعا جديدا من الحشد.
Today, the action takes place in a distant time and place,
واليوم، تجري هذه الأمور في زمن وأماكن متباعدة،
which gives the viewer a sense of detachment from what's happening,
مما يقدم للمشاهد إحساسا بالابتعاد عما يحدث،
a sense of separation.
و شعورا بالانفصال.
It's nothing to do with me.
ليس للأمر أي علاقة بي.
It's already happened.
إذ أنه يحدث بالفعل.
We are also offered an unprecedented sense of intimacy.
كما أنه يعطي انطباعا بالانسجام لم يسبق له مثيل.
Today, we are all offered front row seats.
واليوم تُعرض علينا مقاعد الصف الأول.
We can all watch in private, in our own time and space,
يمكن أن نشاهدها على انفراد، في وقتنا وفضائنا الخاص،
and no one need ever know that we've clicked on the screen to watch.
ولا أحد يحتاج أن يعرف أبدا متى قمنا بفتح الفيديو ومشاهدته.
This sense of separation --
هذا الشعور بالانفصال--
from other people, from the event itself --
عن الاخرين وعن الحدث نفسه--
seems to be key to understanding our ability to watch,
يبدو أنه المفتاح لفهم قدرتنا على مشاهدة.
and there are several ways
حيث توجد عدة طرق
in which the Internet creates a sense of detachment
خلق فيها الإنترنت شعورا بالانفصال
that seems to erode individual moral responsibility.
ويبدو كأنه قام تدريجيا بتدمير المسؤلية الأخلاقية للفرد.
Our activities online are often contrasted with real life,
تعتبر أغلب نشاطاتنا على شبكة الإنترنت مناقضة للواقع،
as though the things we do online are somehow less real.
كما لو أن ما نقوم به على الانترنت يبدو بطريقة ما أقل واقعية.
We feel less accountable for our actions
نشعر بأقل مساءلة عن أفعالنا
when we interact online.
عندما نتفاعل على الإنترنت.
There's a sense of anonymity, a sense of invisibility,
هناك شعور بعدم الكشف عن الهوية، و الشعور بالتخفي،
so we feel less accountable for our behavior.
لذلك نحن نشعر بأقل مساءلة لسلوكنا.
The Internet also makes it far easier to stumble upon things inadvertently,
كما سهّل الاإنترنت البحث عن بعض الأمور بشكل غير مقصور،
things that we would usually avoid in everyday life.
عن الأشياء التي نتجنبها في الحياة اليومية عادةً.
Today, a video can start playing before you even know what you're watching.
اليوم، يمكن أن يبدأ الفيديو حتى قبل أن تعرف ما الذي تشاهده.
Or you may be tempted to look at material that you wouldn't look at in everyday life
أو قد تغريك بعض المواد لمشاهدتها لم تكن تظن أنك ستشاهدها
or you wouldn't look at if you were with other people at the time.
أو لن تقوم بمشاهدتها عندما تكون مع أشخاص في ذلك الوقت.
And when the action is pre-recorded
وعندما يتم تسجيل العمل مسبقا
and takes place in a distant time and space,
ويعرض في مكان و زمان بعيد،
watching seems like a passive activity.
تبدو مشاهدته وكأنه نشاط سلبي.
There's nothing I can do about it now.
لا يوجد شيء أستطيع فعله حيال ذلك الآن.
It's already happened.
إذ أنه يحدث بالفعل.
All these things make it easier as an Internet user
تصبح هذه الأمور أسهل كمتصفح للإنترنت
for us to give in to our sense of curiosity about death,
بالنسبة لنا لإعطاء فرصة لفضولنا عن الموت،
to push our personal boundaries,
لدفع حدودنا الفردية ،
to test our sense of shock, to explore our sense of shock.
لاختبار إحساسنا بالصدمة، و لاستكشاف شعورنا بالصدمة.
But we're not passive when we watch.
لكننا لا نستسلم لما نشاهده،
On the contrary, we're fulfilling the murderer's desire to be seen.
بل على العكس تماما، نحقق رغبة القاتل بأن يتلقى الانتباه.
When the victim of a decapitation is bound and defenseless,
عندما تكون ضحية الذبح مقيدةً وغير مسلحة،
he or she essentially becomes a pawn in their killer's show.
فإنها تصبح كالبيدق خلال العرض الذي سيقدمه القاتل.
Unlike a trophy head that's taken in battle,
وعلى غرار الغنيمة التي يظفر بها أثناء المعركة،
that represents the luck and skill it takes to win a fight,
فإن ذلك يمثل الحظ والمهارة اللازمة لكسب المعركة،
when a beheading is staged,
عندما يتم تنظيم عملية الذبح،
when it's essentially a piece of theater,
عندما تكون بالأساس فصل من عرضٍ مسرحي،
the power comes from the reception the killer receives as he performs.
حيث يستمد القاتل القوة من مشاهديه أثناء قيامه بذلك.
In other words, watching is very much part of the event.
وبعبارة أخرى، تعتبر مشاهدته جزءا لا يتجزأ من هذا الحدث.
The event no longer takes place in a single location
لم يعد الأمر يتخذ له موقعا واحدا
at a certain point in time as it used to and as it may still appear to.
في مرحلة ما محددة كما كان معتادا وكما تبدو عليه.
Now the event is stretched out in time and place,
والآن يمتد هذا الحدث في الزمان والمكان،
and everyone who watches plays their part.
وكل واحد يؤدي دوره.
We should stop watching,
يجب أن نتوقف عن مشاهدة مثل هذه المواد.
but we know we won't.
ولكننا نعرف أننا لن نقوم بذلك.
History tells us we won't,
يخبرنا التاريخ أننا لن نفعل ذلك،
and the killers know it too.
كما أن القتلة على دراية بذلك،
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Bruno Giussani: Thank you. Let me get this back. Thank you.
برونو: شكرا لك. دعيني أسترد هذا. شكرا لك.
Let's move here. While they install for the next performance,
لننتقل إلى هنا. بينما يقومون بالتحضير للعرض التالي،
I want to ask you the question that probably many here have,
أريد طرح سؤال ربما تبادر إلى أذهان الكثير من الحاضرين،
which is how did you get interested in this topic?
وهو كيف أصبحتِ مهتمةً بهذا الموضوع؟
Frances Larson: I used to work at a museum
فرانسس: كنت أعمل في متحف
called the Pitt Rivers Museum in Oxford,
يعرف بمتحف بيت ريفرز في أكسفورد،
which was famous for its display of shrunken heads from South America.
و المشهور بعرضه للرؤوس المتقلصة من أمريكا الجنوبية.
People used to say, "Oh, the shrunken head museum, the shrunken head museum!"
اعتاد الناس تكرار: "أوه، متحف للرؤوس المتقلصة، متحف للرؤوس المتقلصة."
And at the time, I was working on the history
وفي ذلك الوقت، كنت أعمل في قسم التاريخ
of scientific collections of skulls.
الخاص بالمجموعات العلمية عن الجماجم.
I was working on the cranial collections,
كنت أعمل على مجموعة من الجماجم
and it just struck me as ironic
وبدا لي الأمر مثيرا للسخرية
that here were people coming to see this gory, primitive, savage culture
بأن يقوم الناس بزيارة المتحف لرؤية هذه الثقافات الدامية والبدائية والوحشية
that they were almost fantasizing about and creating
حيث أنهم كانوا منبهرين بذلك
without really understanding what they were seeing,
دون أن يفهموا حقا ما كانوا يشاهدونه،
and all the while these vast -- I mean hundreds of thousands
وفي حين أن كل هذا المقدار الضخم - أعني مئات الآلاف
of skulls in our museums, all across Europe and the States --
من الجماجم الموجودة في متاحفنا، من جميع أنحاء أوروبا والولايات المتحدة-
were kind of upholding this Enlightenment pursuit of scientific rationality.
كانت كنوع من الدعم لحركة التنوير الفلسفية الباحثة عن العقلانية العلمية.
So I wanted to kind of twist it round and say, "Let's look at us."
أردت أن أتلاعب بالألفاظ وأقول لكم "لننظر لأنفسنا."
We're looking through the glass case at these shrunken heads.
و نقوم بالنظر إلى هذه الجماجم من خلال حاجز زجاجي.
Let's look at our own history and our own cultural fascination with these things.
دعونا نهتم بتاريخنا وسحر ثقافتنا عن طريق هذه الأمور.
BG: Thank you for sharing that.
برونو: شكرا لك لمشاركتك لنا هذا.
FL: Thank you.
فرانسس: شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)